How many companies have you interacted with today?
كم عدد الشركات التي تواصلت معها اليوم؟
Well, you got up in the morning,
حسنا، لقد استيقظت الصباح
took a shower,
واستحميت،
washed your hair,
وغسلت شعرك،
used a hair dryer,
واستخدمت مجفف الشعر،
ate breakfast --
وأكلت وجبة الفطور ...
ate cereals, fruit, yogurt, whatever --
وأكلت الحبوب والفواكه والزبادي وغيرها
had coffee --
وشربت قهوة ...
tea.
شاي.
You took public transport to come here,
كما استقليت وسائل النقل العام للمجيء هنا
or maybe used your private car.
أو ربما استقليت سيارتك الشخصية.
You interacted with the company that you work for or that you own.
وتواصلت مع الشركة التي تعمل فيها أو تملكها.
You interacted with your clients,
كما تواصلت مع الزبائن،
your customers,
والعملاء،
and so on and so forth.
وهكذا دواليك.
I'm pretty sure there are at least seven companies
أنا متأكد جدا بأن هناك على الأقل سبع شركات
you've interacted with today.
تواصلت معها اليوم.
Let me tell you a stunning statistic.
دعوني اخبركم بإحصائيات مذهلة.
One out of seven large, public corporations
واحدة من أكبر سبع مؤسسات عامة
commit fraud every year.
ترتكب عملية احتيال كل سنة.
This is a US academic study that looks at US companies --
فهذه دراسات أكاديمية أمريكية تفحصت الشركات الأمريكية
I have no reason to believe that it's different in Europe.
ليس لدي سبب لأن أعتقد ذلك وهذا يختلف في أوروبا
This is a study that looks at both detected and undetected fraud
فهذه الدراسة تنظر إلى الاحتيالات المكتشفة وغير المكتشفة
using statistical methods.
مستخدمة طرقا إحصائية.
This is not petty fraud.
وهذا ليس احتيالا صغيرا.
These frauds cost the shareholders of these companies,
وتكلف هذه الإحتيالات المساهمين في هذه الشركات،
and therefore society,
وكذلك المجتمع،
on the order of 380 billion dollars per year.
ما يقارب 380 مليار دولار سنويا.
We can all think of some examples, right?
نستطيع كلنا التفكير في أمثلة، صحيح؟
The car industry's secrets aren't quite so secret anymore.
فأسرار مصانع السيارات لم تعد أسرارًا بعد.
Fraud has become a feature,
وأصبحت الاحتيالات ميزة،
not a bug,
وليست شيئًا سلبيًا،
of the financial services industry.
من قطاع الخدمات المالية.
That's not me who's claiming that,
لست أنا من أدعي ذلك،
that's the president of the American Finance Association
بل رئيس جمعية التمويل الأمريكية
who stated that in his presidential address.
الذي ذكر ذلك في خطابه الرئيسي.
That's a huge problem if you think about, especially,
فهذه مشكلة كبيرة إذا كنت تفكر، خصوصا
an economy like Switzerland,
في اقتصاد دولة كسويسرا،
which relies so much on the trust put into its financial industry.
والذي يعتمد كثيرا على الثقة الملقاة على القطاع المالي
On the other hand,
في جانب آخر،
there are six out of seven companies who actually remain honest
هناك ست من أصل سبع شركات لا يزالون صادقين
despite all temptations to start engaging in fraud.
رغم كل الإغراءات للانخراط في الاحتيال.
There are whistle-blowers like Michael Woodford,
هناك المبلغين عن المخالفات مثل مايكل وودفورد،
who blew the whistle on Olympus.
الذي بلغ عن المخالفات في أوليمبوس
These whistle-blowers risk their careers,
ويهدد هؤلاء المبلغون حياتهم المهنية
their friendships,
وصداقاتهم،
to bring out the truth about their companies.
ليقولوا الحقيقة عن شركاتهم.
There are journalists like Anna Politkovskaya
وهناك صحفيين مثل آنا بوليتكوفسكايا
who risk even their lives to report human rights violations.
والتي خاطرت بحياتها للإبلاغ عن انتهاكات حقوق الإنسان.
She got killed --
فقتلت ...
every year,
وكل سنة،
around 100 journalists get killed
يقتل حوالي 100 صحفي
because of their conviction to bring out the truth.
بسبب قناعاتهم لقول الحقيقة.
So in my talk today,
حتى في حديثي اليوم،
I want to share with you some insights I've obtained and learned
أريد أن أشارككم بعض الأفكار التي حصلت عليها وتعلمتها
in the last 10 years of conducting research in this.
في السنوات العشر الأخيرة من إجراء هذا البحث
I'm a researcher, a scientist working with economists,
فأنا باحث وعالم يعمل مع الاقتصاديين،
financial economists,
ومع الاقتصاديين الماليين،
ethicists, neuroscientists,
مع علماء الأخلاق، علماء الأعصاب،
lawyers and others
مع المحامين وغيرهم
trying to understand what makes humans tick,
محاولا أن أفهم ما يجعل البشر قردا،
and how can we address this issue of fraud in corporations
وكيف يمكننا معالجة الغش في الشركات
and therefore contribute to the improvement of the world.
وبالتالي نساهم في تحسين العالم.
I want to start by sharing with you two very distinct visions
أريد أن أبدأ من خلال تبادل رؤيتين اثنتين مميزتين
of how people behave.
لكيفية تصرف الناس.
First, meet Adam Smith,
أولا، تعرفوا على آدم سميث
founding father of modern economics.
مؤسس الاقتصاد الحديث.
His basic idea was that if everybody behaves in their own self-interests,
وكانت فكرته الأساسية هي إذا كان الجميع يتصرف بمصالحهم الذاتية،
that's good for everybody in the end.
فهذا جيد لكل شخص في النهاية.
Self-interest isn't a narrowly defined concept
فالمصلحة الذاتية ليست مفهوما محدودا
just for your immediate utility.
فقط لمنفعتك الفورية.
It has a long-run implication.
بل إن لها أثرا طويل المدى.
Let's think about that.
دعونا نفكر في ذلك.
Think about this dog here.
فكروا في هذا الكلب هنا.
That might be us.
قد نكون نحن ذلك الكلب.
There's this temptation --
فهناك هذا الإغراء ...
I apologize to all vegetarians, but --
أعتذر لكل النباتيين، ولكن ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Dogs do like the bratwurst.
تحب الكلاب النقانق.
Now, the straight-up, self-interested move here
والآن، ينتقل الأمناء، والمهتمين بأنفسهم هنا
is to go for that.
للذهاب لهذا الشيء.
So my friend Adam here might jump up,
فصديقي آدم هنا ربما يقفز،
get the sausage and thereby ruin all this beautiful tableware.
للحصول على النقانق وبالتالي تخريب كل أدوات هذه المائدة الجميلة.
But that's not what Adam Smith meant.
ولكن ليس هذا ما يعنيه آدم سميث.
He didn't mean disregard all consequences --
فهو لا يعني تجاهل كل العواقب ...
to the contrary.
على العكس من ذلك.
He would have thought,
كان يعتقد،
well, there may be negative consequences,
حسنا، قد تكون هناك عواقب سلبية،
for example,
على سبيل المثال،
the owner might be angry with the dog
قد يكون المالك غاضبا من الكلب
and the dog, anticipating that, might not behave in this way.
والكلب، متوقعا ذلك، لا يتصرف بهذه الطريقة.
That might be us,
قد نكون نحن ذلك،
weighing the benefits and costs of our actions.
نزن الفوائد وتكاليف أعمالنا.
How does that play out?
كيف يتم ذلك؟
Well, many of you, I'm sure,
حسنا، الكثير منكم، أنا متاكد،
have in your companies,
لديهم في شركاتكم،
especially if it's a large company,
خاصة إذا كانت شركة كبيرة،
a code of conduct.
مدونة قواعد السلوك.
And then if you behave according to that code of conduct,
وإذا تصرفت وفقا لمدونة قواعد السلوك هذه،
that improves your chances of getting a bonus payment.
فهذا يحسن من فرصك للحصول على مكافأة.
And on the other hand, if you disregard it,
وفي جانب آخر، إذا تجاهلتها،
then there are higher chances of not getting your bonus
فهناك فرص أعلى من عدم حصولك على المكافأة
or its being diminished.
أو تناقصها.
In other words,
بمعنى آخر،
this is a very economic motivation
هذا دافع اقتصادي للغاية
of trying to get people to be more honest,
من محاولة الحصول على أناس صادقين،
or more aligned with the corporation's principles.
أو أكثر اتساقا مع مبادئ الشركة.
Similarly, reputation is a very powerful economic force, right?
وبالمثل، فالسمعة قوة اقتصادية قوية جدا، أليس كذلك؟
We try to build a reputation,
نحاول أن نبني سمعه،
maybe for being honest,
ربما لنكون صادقين،
because then people trust us more in the future.
لكي يثق الناس بنا في المستقبل.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
Adam Smith talked about the baker
تحدث سميث عن الخباز
who's not producing good bread out of his benevolence
الذي لا ينتج خبزا جيدا من خيره
for those people who consume the bread,
وذلك بالنسبة لأولئك الناس الذين يستهلكون الخبز،
but because he wants to sell more future bread.
ولكنه يريد أن يبيع المزيد من الخبز في المستقبل.
In my research, we find, for example,
في بحثي، نجد، على سبيل المثال،
at the University of Zurich,
في جامعة زيورخ،
that Swiss banks who get caught up in media,
أن البنوك السويسرية الضالعة في وسائل الإعلام،
and in the context, for example,
وفي السياق، على سبيل المثال،
of tax evasion, of tax fraud,
من التهرب الضريبي، والاحتيال الضريبي،
have bad media coverage.
لديها تغطية سيئة في وسائل الإعلام.
They lose net new money in the future
يفقدون صافي أموالهم الجديدة في المستقبل
and therefore make lower profits.
وبالتالي الحصول على أرباح أقل.
That's a very powerful reputational force.
هذه سمعة قوية جدا.
Benefits and costs.
الفوائد والتكاليف.
Here's another viewpoint of the world.
وهنا نظرة أخرى من العالم.
Meet Immanuel Kant,
تعرفوا على ايمانويل كانت،
18th-century German philosopher superstar.
النجم الفيلسوفي الألماني في القرن الثامن عشر.
He developed this notion
لقد طور هذه النظرية
that independent of the consequences,
التي هي مستقلة عن العواقب،
some actions are just right
تكون بعض الأفعال محقة
and some are just wrong.
والبعض الآخر خطأ.
It's just wrong to lie, for example.
إنه من الخطأ أن تكذب، على سبيل المثال.
So, meet my friend Immanuel here.
لذلك، قابلوا صديقي ايمانويل هنا.
He knows that the sausage is very tasty,
فهو يعلم بأن النقانق طيبة المذاق،
but he's going to turn away because he's a good dog.
لكنه سوف يرفض لأنه كلب جيد.
He knows it's wrong to jump up
وهو يعلم بأنه من الخطأ أن تقفز
and risk ruining all this beautiful tableware.
وخطر تخريب كل أدوات هذه المائدة الجميلة.
If you believe that people are motivated like that,
فإذا اعتقدت بأن لدى الناس دوافع كهذه،
then all the stuff about incentives,
ثم كل الأشياء عن الحوافز،
all the stuff about code of conduct and bonus systems and so on,
جميع الأشياء حول مدونة قواعد السلوك ونظم المكافآت وهلم جرا،
doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
ليس لها أي معنى
People are motivated by different values perhaps.
الناس متحمسون حسب قيم مختلفة ربما.
So, what are people actually motivated by?
إذن، ما الذي يجعل الناس متحفزين؟
These two gentlemen here have perfect hairdos,
فهذان السيدان هنا لديهما تسريحة شعر جميلة،
but they give us very different views of the world.
ولكن لديهما رأيين مختلفين عن العالم.
What do we do with this?
ما الذي نفعله مع هذا الشيء؟
Well, I'm an economist
حسنا، فأنا خبير اقتصادي
and we conduct so-called experiments to address this issue.
ونقوم بإجراء التجارب لمعالجة هذه المسألة.
We strip away facts which are confusing in reality.
نحن نبعد الحقائق المربكة في الواقع.
Reality is so rich, there is so much going on,
فالواقع غني جدا، وهناك كثير مستمر،
it's almost impossible to know what drives people's behavior really.
فإنه من المستحيل معرفة ما يدفع سلوك الناس حقا.
So let's do a little experiment together.
لذا دعونا نجري بعض التجارب معا.
Imagine the following situation.
تخيلوا الوضع التالي.
You're in a room alone,
أنت وحدك في غرفة،
not like here.
ليس كهذه الغرفة.
There's a five-franc coin like the one I'm holding up right now
هناك عملة خمسة فرنك مثل التي أمسكها الآن
in front of you.
أمامكم.
Here are your instructions:
وهنا التعليمات الموجهة لكم:
toss the coin four times,
إرم العملة أربع مرات،
and then on a computer terminal in front of you,
ومن ثم على محطة الكمبيوتر أمامك،
enter the number of times tails came up.
أدخل عدد المرات التي تظهر فيها علامة الذيل.
This is the situation.
هذا هو الوضع.
Here's the rub.
هنا المشكلة.
For every time that you announce that you had a tails throw,
في كل مرة تعلن فيها أن علامة الذيل ظهرت،
you get paid five francs.
ستحصل على خمسة فرنكات.
So if you say I had two tails throws,
فإذا قلت حصلت على علامة الذيل مرتين،
you get paid 10 francs.
ستحصل على 10 فرنكات.
If you say you had zero, you get paid zero francs.
وإذا لم تحصل على هذه العلامة، ستحصل على لا شيء.
If you say, "I had four tails throws,"
وإذا قلت "حصلت على أربع منها"
then you get paid 20 francs.
ستحصل على عشرين فرنكا.
It's anonymous,
إنها غير معروفة،
nobody's watching what you're doing,
لا أحد يراقب ما تفعله،
and you get paid that money anonymously.
وستحصل على المال بصورة غير علنية.
I've got two questions for you.
ولدي سؤالين لكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know what's coming now, right?
تعلمون ما الذي سيأتي الآن، صحيح؟
First, how would you behave in that situation?
أولا، كيف تتصرفون في هذه الحالة؟
The second, look to your left and look to your right --
ثانيا، انظر شمالا ويمينا ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and think about how the person sitting next to you
وفكر كيف يجلس الشخص اإلى جانبك
might behave in that situation.
ربما تتصرف في تلك الحالة.
We did this experiment for real.
لقد قمنا بهذه التجربة في الحقيقة.
We did it at the Manifesta art exhibition
فعلنا ذلك في معرض مانيفيستا للفن
that took place here in Zurich recently,
والذي كان هنا في زيورخ مؤخرا،
not with students in the lab at the university
ليس مع الطلاب في مختبر الجامعة
but with the real population,
ولكن مع أناس حقيقيون،
like you guys.
مثلكم يا أصدقاء.
First, a quick reminder of stats.
أولا، تذكير صحيح للإحصائيات.
If I throw the coin four times and it's a fair coin,
إذا رميت عملة أربع مرات وهي عملة عادلة،
then the probability that it comes up four times tails
ثم من المحتمل بأن تأتي أربع مرات علامة الذيل
is 6.25 percent.
6.25 %
And I hope you can intuitively see
وآمل أن تتمكنوا من أن تروا بحدس
that the probability that all four of them are tails is much lower
بأن احتمالية أن تكون الأربعة علامة الذيل أقل بكثير
than if two of them are tails, right?
من أن تكون اثنتان منهم علامة الذيل، صحيح؟
Here are the specific numbers.
إليكم الأرقام المحددة.
Here's what happened.
وهنا ما حدث.
People did this experiment for real.
قام الناس بهذه التجربة حقيقة.
Around 30 to 35 percent of people said,
قال حوالي 30 إلى35 % من الناس،
"Well, I had four tails throws."
"حسنا، لقد حصلت على أربع وجهات من الذيل "
That's extremely unlikely.
هذا أمر مستبعد للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the really amazing thing here,
ولكن الشيء المدهش هنا،
perhaps to an economist,
ربما لخبير اقتصادي،
is there are around 65 percent of people who did not say I had four tails throws,
بأن هناك حوالي 65 % من الناس الذين لم يقولوا كان لي 4 وجهات من الذيل،
even though in that situation,
رغم أنه في هذه الحالة،
nobody's watching you,
لا أحد يشاهدك،
the only consequence that's in place
والنتيجة الوحيدة الموجودة
is you get more money if you say four than less.
هي الحصول على المزيد من المال إذا قلت أربعة من أقل.
You leave 20 francs on the table by announcing zero.
يمكنك ترك 20 فرنك على الطاولة إذا أعلنت عن حصولك على صفر.
I don't know whether the other people all were honest
لا أعرف ما إذا كان الآخرون كلهم صادقون
or whether they also said a little bit higher or lower than what they did
أو ما إذا كانوا أيضا قالوا أعلى قليلا أو أقل مما حصلوا
because it's anonymous.
لأنها غير معروفة.
We only observed the distribution.
نحن لاحظنا التوزيع فقط.
But what I can tell you -- and here's another coin toss.
ولكن ما يمكنني قوله ... وهنا عملة أخرى مرمية.
There you go, it's tails.
ها نحن ذا، إنها واجهة الذيل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't check, OK?
لا تتفحصوها، حسنا؟
What I can tell you
ما يمكنني إخباركم به
is that not everybody behaved like Adam Smith would have predicted.
هو أن الجميع لا يتصرفون مثلما كان آدم سميث يتوقع.
So what does that leave us with?
فما الذي ترك لنا ذلك؟
Well, it seems people are motivated by certain intrinsic values
حسنا، يبدو أن الناس متحفزين بقيم جوهرية معينة
and in our research, we look at this.
وفي بحثنا، نظرنا إلى هذا.
We look at the idea that people have so-called protected values.
نظرنا إلى فكرة أن الناس لديهم ما يسمى قيم محمية.
A protected value isn't just any value.
القيمة المحمية ليست فقط أي قيمة.
A protected value is a value where you're willing to pay a price
إن القيمة المحمية هي القيمة التي ترغب في دفع سعر لها
to uphold that value.
لدعم تلك القيمة.
You're willing to pay a price to withstand the temptation to give in.
كنت على استعداد لدفع ثمن لتحمل الإغراء المعطى.
And the consequence is you feel better
والنتيجة هي أنك تشعر بشكل أفضل
if you earn money in a way that's consistent with your values.
إذا كنت تكسب المال بطريقة تتفق مع قيمك.
Let me show you this again in the metaphor of our beloved dog here.
اسمحوا لي أن أريكم هذا مرة أخرى في استعارة كلبنا الحبيب هنا.
If we succeed in getting the sausage without violating our values,
فإذا نجحنا في الحصول على النقانق دون انتهاك قيمنا،
then the sausage tastes better.
فسيكون ذوقها أفضل.
That's what our research shows.
وهذا ما أظهره بحثنا.
If, on the other hand,
إذا، من ناحية أخرى،
we do so --
عملنا ذلك ...
if we get the sausage
وإذا حصلنا على النقانق
and in doing so we actually violate values,
وبذلك نكون قد انتهكنا القيم بالفعل،
we value the sausage less.
نحن نقيم النقانق بشكل أقل.
Quantitatively, that's quite powerful.
بصورة كمية، هذا قوي جدا.
We can measure these protected values,
نستطيع قياس هذه القيم المحمية،
for example,
على سبيل المثال،
by a survey measure.
من خلال إجراء دراسة.
Simple, nine-item survey that's quite predictive in these experiments.
ببساطة فإن دراسة من تسعة بنود تنبأ تماما في هذه التجارب.
If you think about the average of the population
وإذا فكرنا في متوسط السكان
and then there's a distribution around it --
ومن ثم هناك توزيع حوله ...
people are different, we all are different.
فالناس مختلفين، ونحن أيضا كذلك.
People who have a set of protected values
الناس الذين لديهم مجموعة من القيم المحمية
that's one standard deviation above the average,
وهذا انحراف معياري فوق المتوسط،
they discount money they receive by lying by about 25 percent.
فإنهم ينقصون المال الذي يتلقونه عن طريق الكذب بنحو 25 في المئة.
That means a dollar received when lying
وهذا يعني أن تتلقى دولار عندما تكذب
is worth to them only 75 cents
تكون قيمته لهم فقط 75 سنتا
without any incentives you put in place for them to behave honestly.
دون أي حوافز يضعونها ليتصرفوا بأمانة.
It's their intrinsic motivation.
إنها دوافعهم الذاتية.
By the way, I'm not a moral authority.
بالمناسبة، أنا لست سلطة أخلاقية.
I'm not saying I have all these beautiful values, right?
أنا لا أقول لدي كل هذه القيم الجميلة، صحيح؟
But I'm interested in how people behave
ولكن أنا مهتم في كيف يتصرف الناس
and how we can leverage that richness in human nature
وكيف يمكننا الاستفادة من هذا الثراء في الطبيعة البشرية
to actually improve the workings of our organizations.
لتحسين عمل منظماتنا بالفعل.
So there are two very, very different visions here.
لذا هناك رؤيتان مختلفتان جدا جدا هنا.
On the one hand,
من الناحية الأولى،
you can appeal to benefits and costs
يمكنك أن تلتمس الفوائد والتكاليف
and try to get people to behave according to them.
ومحاولة اقناع الناس بأن يتصرفوا وفقا لهم.
On the other hand,
ومن ناحية أخرى،
you can select people who have the values
يمكنك اختيار الأشخاص الذين لديهم القيم
and the desirable characteristics, of course --
والخصال المرغوب فيها، بالطبع ...
competencies that go in line with your organization.
والكفاءات التي تتماشى مع مؤسستك.
I do not yet know where these protected values really come from.
لا أعرف حتى الآن من أين تأتي هذه القيم المحمية حقا.
Is it nurture or is it nature?
هل هي تغذية أم طبيعة؟
What I can tell you
ما أستطيع قوله لكم
is that the distribution looks pretty similar for men and women.
هو أن التوزيع يبدو مشابها جدا للرجال والنساء.
It looks pretty similar for those who had studied economics
إنه يبدو مشابها لأولئك الذين درسوا علم الاقتصاد
or those who had studied psychology.
أو أولئك الذين درسوا علم النفس.
It looks even pretty similar around different age categories
يبدو حتى مشابه جدا لفئات عمرية مختلفة
among adults.
بين البالغين.
But I don't know yet how this develops over a lifetime.
ولكن أنا لا أعرف حتى الآن كيف يتطور هذا على مدى العمر.
That will be the subject of future research.
سيكون هذا عنوان البحث المستقبلي.
The idea I want to leave you with
إن الفكرة التي أود أن أترككم معها
is it's all right to appeal to incentives.
هي هل من حقنا أن نلتمس الحوافز.
I'm an economist;
أنا خبير اقتصادي،
I certainly believe in the fact that incentives work.
وأعتقد حقا في الواقع بأن للحوافز دور.
But do think about selecting the right people
ولكن فكر في اختيار الأشخاص المناسبين
rather than having people and then putting incentives in place.
بدلا من أن يكون هناك أشخاص ومن ثم وضع الحوافز قيد التنفيذ.
Selecting the right people with the right values
إن اختيار الأشخاص المناسبين مع القيم الصحيحة
may go a long way to saving a lot of trouble
قد يساعد في حفظ الكثير من المتاعب
and a lot of money
والكثير من المال
in your organizations.
في منظماتكم.
In other words,
بمعنى آخر،
it will pay off to put people first.
سوف تربح لوضع الناس أولا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)